{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "__________was imprisoned for the rest of his life by Aurangzeb",
            "optionA": "  Akbar ",
            "optionB": "  Shah Jahan ",
            "optionC": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionD": "  Babur ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Although Shah Jahan fully recovered from his illness, Aurangzeb declared him incompetent to rule and put him under house arrest in Agra Fort. Shah Jahan was imprisoned by his son Aurangzeb in Red Fort (Agra). ",
            "keyString": "991467s17m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian Mughal paintings originated during the rule of which Mughal Emperor?",
            "optionA": "  Humayun ",
            "optionB": "  Akbar ",
            "optionC": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionD": "  Shah Jahan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMughal Paintings originated during the rule of Humayun, especially when he brought two Persian artists Mir-Sayyid Ali and Abd-us-samad to India. ",
            "keyString": "991499s17m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The rulers of Vijayanagar promoted",
            "optionA": "  Hindi, Marathi and Sanskrit ",
            "optionB": "  Malayalam, Tamil and Sanskrit ",
            "optionC": "  Tamil, Telugu and Sanskrit ",
            "optionD": "  Telugu, Urdu and Sanskrit ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t The ruler of Vijaynagar Empire patronised Kannada, Tamil, Telugu and Sanskrit Scholars. ",
            "keyString": "991513s17m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Sayyid dynasty of the Delhi Sultanate is called so because__________?",
            "optionA": "  Its founder and his successors adopted the title Sayyid ",
            "optionB": "  Its founder and his successors belonged to the Sayyid tribe of eastern Turkistan ",
            "optionC": "  Its founder and his successors were descendant of the prophet Muhammad ",
            "optionD": "  Its founder was a scholar of Islamic theology ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKhizr Khan was the founder of the Sayyid Dynasty. He did not assume any royal title. He professed to rule as the Viceroy of Timur's son and successor Shah Rukh. His dynasty has been called the Sayyid dynasty because it was believed that he was a descendant of Prophet Muhammad. ",
            "keyString": "991525s17m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the founder of Lodi dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  Daulat Khan Lodi ",
            "optionB": "  Sikandar Lodi ",
            "optionC": "  Bahlol Lodi ",
            "optionD": "  Ibrahim Lodi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Lodi dynasty (or Lodhi) was an Afghan dynasty that ruled the Delhi Sultanate from 1451 to 1526. It was the last dynasty of the Delhi Sultanate, and was founded by Bahlul Khan Lodi when he replaced the Sayyid dynasty. ",
            "keyString": "991537s17m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Prince Salim was the name of the future Emperor__________",
            "optionA": "  Babur ",
            "optionB": "  Humayun ",
            "optionC": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionD": "  Akbar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMirza Nur-ud-din Beig Muhammad Khan Salim known by his imperial name Jahangir (31 August 1569 \u2013 28 October 1627), was the fourth Mughal Emperor who ruled from 1605 until his death in 1627. ",
            "keyString": "38819s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Prince Khurram was the name of the future Emperor__________",
            "optionA": "  Shah Jahan ",
            "optionB": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionC": "  Babur ",
            "optionD": "  Akbar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMirza Shahab-ud-din Baig Muhammad Khan Khurram (5 January 1592 \u2013 22 January 1666), better known by his regional name Shah Jahan (\"King of the World\"), was the fifth Mughal emperor, who reigned from 1628 to 1658. ",
            "keyString": "38863s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following powers did not fight for the Tungabhadra Doab?",
            "optionA": "  Pallavas and Chalukyas ",
            "optionB": "  Cholas and later Chalukyas of Kalyana ",
            "optionC": "  Golconda and Ahmadnagar Sultanates ",
            "optionD": "  Vijayanagar and Bahmani kingdoms ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Golconda and Ahmadnagar Sultanates did not fight for the Tungabhadra Doab. ",
            "keyString": "38969s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Red fort in Delhi was the residence of emperors of which dynasty in the 16th century?",
            "optionA": "  Rajput ",
            "optionB": "  Khalji ",
            "optionC": "  Tughlaq ",
            "optionD": "  Mughal ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Red Fort was commissioned by Mughal Emperor Shah Jahan in the 17th century, it was the main residence of the Mughal emperors for nearly 200 years. ",
            "keyString": "39064s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the capital of Pallava Dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  Kanchipuram ",
            "optionB": "  Tiruchirapalli ",
            "optionC": "  Tanjore ",
            "optionD": "  Chennai ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKanchipuram was the capital of Pallava dynasty. Bappadev was the founder of Pallava dynasty, the famous ruler of the dynasty was Narsihman Verman 1st. ",
            "keyString": "39155s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the last ruler of Lodi Dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  Bahlol Lodi ",
            "optionB": "  Ibrahim Lodi ",
            "optionC": "  Daulat Khan Lodi ",
            "optionD": "  Sikandar Lodi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIbrahim Lodhi was the last ruler of Lodhi Dynasty. He was defeated and killed in the First battle of Panipat in 1526 by Babur. He was the third ruler of Lodhi Dynasty. His grandfather Bahlol Lodhi was the first and founder ruler of this dynasty. ",
            "keyString": "96569s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Chand Bibi the famous Muslim ruler belonged to which kingdom?",
            "optionA": "  Bijapur ",
            "optionB": "  Golconda ",
            "optionC": "  Ahmednagar ",
            "optionD": "  Berar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChand Bibi (1550\u20131599 CE), was an Indian Muslim regent and warrior. She acted as the Regent of Bijapur (1580\u201390) and Regent of Ahmednagar (in current day Maharashtra) (1596\u201399). Chand Bibi is best known for defending Ahmednagar against the Mughal forces of Emperor Akbar in 1595. ",
            "keyString": "96761s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which dynasty was ruling in Vijaynagar empire at the time of the Battle of Talikota?",
            "optionA": "  Sangam ",
            "optionB": "  Aravidu ",
            "optionC": "  Tuluva ",
            "optionD": "  Saluva ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTuluva Dynasty was the third dynasty to rule Vijaynagar Empire. The Battle of Talikota was fought between the Deccan Sultanates and Vijaynagar Kingdom.Sadasiva Raya of Tuluva dynasty was the emperor of Vijaynagar at the time of the Battle of Talikota. ",
            "keyString": "96920s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "__________first became the capital of a kingdom under the Tomar Rajputs",
            "optionA": "  Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Patliputra ",
            "optionC": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionD": "  Taxila ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDelhi first became the capital of a kingdom only under the Tomaras who were a part of the Rajput dynasties. The Tomara Rajputs were defeated in the mid-twelfth century by the Chauhans. Delhi became an important commercial centre under the Tomaras and Chauhans. ",
            "keyString": "97075s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following battles led to the foundation of the Mughal rule at Delhi?",
            "optionA": "  Third Battle of Panipat ",
            "optionB": "  Second Battle of Panipat ",
            "optionC": "  Battle of Haldighati ",
            "optionD": "  First Battle of Panipat ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe First Battle of Panipat, on 21 April 1526, was fought between the invading forces of Babur and the Lodi Kingdom. It took place in north India and marked the beginning of the Mughal Empire and the end of the Delhi Sultanate. ",
            "keyString": "97230s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many Mahajanapadas were there in ancient India?",
            "optionA": "  20 ",
            "optionB": "  16 ",
            "optionC": "  18 ",
            "optionD": "  10 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn ancient India 16 Mahajanapadas were mentioned in Anguttar Nakaya. ",
            "keyString": "202445s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The capital of the Bahmani Kings was",
            "optionA": "  Gulbarga ",
            "optionB": "  Bijapur ",
            "optionC": "  Hampi ",
            "optionD": "  Agra ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Bahmani capital was Ahsanabad (Gulbarga) between 1347 and 1425, when it was moved to Muhammadabad (Bidar). ",
            "keyString": "202486s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the founder of Kushan Empire?",
            "optionA": "  Kanishka ",
            "optionB": "  Virna Kadphises ",
            "optionC": "  Kujula Kadphises ",
            "optionD": "  Vasiskha ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKujula Kadphises was the first Yueh Chi chief who crossed the Hindukush Mountains and laid down the foundation of the Kushana Empire. ",
            "keyString": "202502s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who got the monumental 'Rayagopurams' in front of the temples at Hampi, Tiru-pati, etc., constructed?",
            "optionA": "  Vidyaranya ",
            "optionB": "  Krishnadeva Raya ",
            "optionC": "  Harihara ",
            "optionD": "  Raja raj ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t'Rayagopuram' means grand entrance tower of the temple Vijaynagar King Krishnadeva Raya constructed 'Rayagopurams' in front of the temples at Hampi, Tiruvannamalai, Chidambaram Srirangam, Tirupati etc. ",
            "keyString": "202514s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following did not rule the Delhi Sultanate?",
            "optionA": "  Slave dynasty ",
            "optionB": "  Sayyed dynasty ",
            "optionC": "  Khalji dynasty ",
            "optionD": "  Ghori dynasty ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGhori dynasty did not ruled Delhi Sultanate directly, his slaves ruled over India after the death of Ghori. The Slave Dynasty ruled the Sub-continent for about 84 years. It was the first Muslim dynasty that ruled India. Qutub-ud-din Aibak, a slave of Muhammad Ghori, who became the ruler after the death of his master, founded the Slave Dynasty. ",
            "keyString": "267710s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Group of Monuments at Hampi was built by?",
            "optionA": "  Harihara and Bukka ",
            "optionB": "  Udayin and Shishunaga ",
            "optionC": "  Devavarman and Vainya ",
            "optionD": "  Mahendraverman and Sirmara ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHampi, a village and a temple town in Karnataka is one of the most historically rich places. And because Hampi was the capital, it flourished in trade. We have listed down the four different dynasties with small information about each one of them. Sangama Dynasty was founded by Bukka Raya 1 and Harihara 1. The monuments at Hampi was built by the founder of Vijay Nagar dynasty i.e. Harihar and Bukka. ",
            "keyString": "267744s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is considered as the greatest of all the Vijayanagar rulers?",
            "optionA": "  Krishnadeva Raya ",
            "optionB": "  Vir Narasimha ",
            "optionC": "  Sadasiva Raya ",
            "optionD": "  Rama Raya ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKrishna Deva Raya (1509-29) is considered as the greatest of all the Vijayanagar rulers for his military as well as literary and other achievements. Krishnadeva Raya was the third ruler of Tuluva dynasty. He ruled from Vijaynagar Empire from 1509-1529. He was given the titles of 'Andhra Bhoja' Mooru Rayara Ganda (King of three Kings) and Kannada Rajya Rama Ramana. ",
            "keyString": "267760s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The medieval city of Vijayanagar is now known as",
            "optionA": "  Chandragiri ",
            "optionB": "  Aravidu ",
            "optionC": "  Hampi ",
            "optionD": "  Kondavidu ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHampi, also referred to as the Group of Monuments at Hampi, is a UNESCO World Heritage Site located in east-central Karnataka, India. It became the centre of the Hindu Vijayanagara Empire capital in the 14th century. ",
            "keyString": "267772s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first Vijayanagar ruler to wrest the important fort of Goa from the Bahamanis?",
            "optionA": "  Reva Rayali ",
            "optionB": "  Harihara-I ",
            "optionC": "  Harihara-II ",
            "optionD": "  Bukka-I ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHarihara-II was the first ruler of Vijaynagar to seize important fort of Goa from the Bahamanis. ",
            "keyString": "267784s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gol Gumbaz was built in which century?",
            "optionA": "  15th ",
            "optionB": "  16th ",
            "optionC": "  17th ",
            "optionD": "  18th ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t An ancient structure, the Gol Gumbaz is a prominent historical monument in Bijapur. Built in the 17th century, it houses the tomb of the city's legendary ruler, Adil Shah. It is especially renowned for the architectural finesse of its Indo-Islamic style structure. ",
            "keyString": "332297s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Bahmani Kingdom was founded by",
            "optionA": "  Ahmad Shah-I ",
            "optionB": "  Alauddin Hasan ",
            "optionC": "  Mahmud Gavan ",
            "optionD": "  Firoz shah Bahmani ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Bahmani kingdom was founded by Alauddin Hasan in 1347. After his coronation, he assumed the title of Alauddin Hasan Bahman Shah (1347-58), it is from this title that the kingdom was called the Bahmani kingdom.",
            "keyString": "332512s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Arabic work of Al-Biruni that gave an account of the subcontinent is called__________",
            "optionA": "  Kitab - AI Hind ",
            "optionB": "  Kitab - Al Bharat ",
            "optionC": "  Pustak - AI Hind ",
            "optionD": "  Pustak - AI Bharat ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAl-biruni was a Arabian scholar with great knowledge of philosopher, mathematician, etc. He came India with Mahmud of Ghazani (Mahmud Ghazanavi). He wrote the book Kitab - AI Hind(after exploring India).",
            "keyString": "332646s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Buland Darwaza is located in",
            "optionA": "  West Bengal ",
            "optionB": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionC": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBuland Darwaza, or the \"Gate of victory\", was built in 1572 A.D. by Mughal emperor Akbar to commemorate his victory over Gujarat. It is the main entrance to the palace at Fatehpur Sikri, Uttar Pradesh which is 43 km from Agra, India. Buland Darwaza is the highest gateway in the world and is an example of Mughal architecture. ",
            "keyString": "332840s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Charminar was built by?",
            "optionA": "  Humayun ",
            "optionB": "  Mohammad Quli Qutub Shah ",
            "optionC": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionD": "  Narasimha ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe fifth ruler of the Qutb Shahi dynasty Sultan Muhammad Quli Qutb Shah built the Charminar in 1591. After shifting his capital from Golkonda to Hyderabad he built a big structure of Charminar. Because of Charminar this landmark became a global icon of Hyderabad. ",
            "keyString": "332935s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Dara Shikoh was killed in conflict with his brother__________",
            "optionA": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionB": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "optionC": "  Babur ",
            "optionD": "  Shahjahan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the war of succession which ensued after Shah Jahan's illness in 1657, Dara was defeated by his younger brother Prince Muhiuddin (later, the Emperor Aurangzeb). He was executed in 1659 on Aurangzeb's orders in a bitter struggle for the imperial throne. ",
            "keyString": "406694s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which dynasty came to power in India after the Tughlaq dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  The Guptas ",
            "optionB": "  The Khaljis ",
            "optionC": "  The Mughals ",
            "optionD": "  The Sayyids ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe tomb of Muhammad Shah at Lodi Gardens, New Delhi. The Sayyid dynasty was the fourth dynasty of the Delhi Sultanate, with four rulers ruling from 1414 to 1451. Founded by Khizr Khan a former governor of Multan, they succeeded the Tughlaq dynasty and ruled the sultanate until they were displaced by the Lodi dynasty. ",
            "keyString": "406725s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": " Krishnadevaraya maintained friendly relations with the",
            "optionA": "  French ",
            "optionB": "  British ",
            "optionC": "  Protuguese ",
            "optionD": "  Dutch ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Krishnadevaraya established friendly relations with the Portuguese, who set up the Portuguese Dominion of India in Goa in 1510. ",
            "keyString": "406738s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following pair is incorrect?",
            "optionA": "  Hiuen Tsang  -  China ",
            "optionB": "  Ibn Battuta  -  Morocco ",
            "optionC": "  Megasthenes   -  Greece ",
            "optionD": "  Fa-Hien   -  Malaysia ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFa-Hien was a Chinese traveller who came India in the reign of Chandragupta-II. He was Buddhist Monk andhis main aim was to established Buddhism.",
            "keyString": "406750s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the founder of the city of Agra?",
            "optionA": "  Firoz Tughlaq ",
            "optionB": "  Muhammad-bin-Tughlaq ",
            "optionC": "  Alauddin Khalji ",
            "optionD": "  Sikandar Lodi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSikander Lodi made a treaty with Alauddin Hussain Shah and his kingdom of Bengal. In 1503, he commissioned the building of the present-day city of Agra. Agra was founded by him. ",
            "keyString": "406762s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Battle of Panipat was fought in the year 1526 between Babur and__________",
            "optionA": "  Rana Sanga ",
            "optionB": "  Muhammad Bin Tughlaq ",
            "optionC": "  Hemu ",
            "optionD": "  Ibrahim Lodi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe First Battle of Panipat, on 21 April 1526, was fought between the invading forces of Babur and the Ibrahim Lodi Kingdom. It took place in north India and marked the beginning of the Mughal Empire and the end of the Delhi Sultanate. ",
            "keyString": "488795s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Prithviraja-III (1168-1192) was a best known  __________ruler",
            "optionA": "  Chauhan ",
            "optionB": "  Gahadavala ",
            "optionC": "  Chalukya ",
            "optionD": "  Brahmana ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Chahamanas, or Chauhans dynasty ruled over the region around Delhi and Ajmer in 12th century. The best-known Chahamana ruler was Prithviraja III (1168-1192), who defeated an Afghan ruler named Sultan Muhammad Ghori in 1191, but lost to him the very next year, in 1192. ",
            "keyString": "488833s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which battle led to the downfall of the Vijayanagar empire?",
            "optionA": "  Battle of Takkolam ",
            "optionB": "  Battle of Talikota ",
            "optionC": "  Battle of Khanwa ",
            "optionD": "  Battle of Panipat ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of Talikota (23 January 1565) was a watershed battle fought between the Vijayanagara Empire and the Deccan sultanates. The Deccan Sultanates had better artillery, better cavalry and the betrayal by Gilani Brothers (key commanders of Vijaynagar Kingdom) led to the downfall of vijaynagar kingdom. ",
            "keyString": "488853s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mongols under__________ invaded Transoxiana in north-east Iran in 1219",
            "optionA": "  Timur Lang ",
            "optionB": "  Nadir Shah ",
            "optionC": "  Ahmed Shah Abdali ",
            "optionD": "  Genghis Khan ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Mongols under Genghis Khan invaded Transoxiana in north-east Iran in 1219 and the Delhi Sultanate faced their onslaught soon after. Mongol attacks on the Delhi Sultanate increased during the reign of Alauddin Khalji and in the early years of Muhammad Tughluq's rule. ",
            "keyString": "488867s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Akbar was__________ years old when he became emperor",
            "optionA": "  16 ",
            "optionB": "  19 ",
            "optionC": "  13 ",
            "optionD": "  10 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAkbar succeeded Humayun on 14 February 1556, while in the midst of a war against Sikandar Shah to reclaim the Mughal throne. In Kalanaur, Punjab, the 13-year-old Akbar was enthroned by Bairam Khan on a newly constructed platform, which still stands. He was proclaimed Shahanshah (Persian for \"King of Kings\"). ",
            "keyString": "488882s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Krishnadevaraya built the Krishnaswami temple in Hampi, which is situated in the\npresent state of",
            "optionA": "  Karnataka ",
            "optionB": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionC": "  Jammu & Kashmir ",
            "optionD": "  Kerala ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Krishna Swami Temple was built by Ruler Krishnadeva Raya in 1513 AD at Hampi (Karnataka). ",
            "keyString": "567321s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The correct chronological order in which they were built is:\n1. Tughluqabad Fort\n2. Lodi Garden\n3. Qutub Minar\n4. Fatehpur Sikri",
            "optionA": "  3, 1, 4, 2  ",
            "optionB": "  3, 1, 2, 4 ",
            "optionC": "  1, 3, 2, 4 ",
            "optionD": "  1, 3, 4, 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:[1]. Tughlaqabad Fort is a ruined fort in Delhi, built by Ghiyas-ud-din Tughlaq, the founder of Tughlaq dynasty, of the Delhi Sultanate of India in 1321, as he established the fourth historic city of Delhi, which was later abandoned in 1327.[3]. Qutab Minar - Qutab-ud-din Aibak, the first Muslim ruler of Delhi, commenced the construction of thein 1200 AD, but could only finish the basement. His successor, Iltutmush, added three more storeys, and in 1368, Firoz Shah Tughlak constructed the fifth and the last storey.[2]. Lodi garden was built during the Lodi dynasty sometime between 1451 and 1526. A mosque can be seen in the complex which has three domes and five arched openings.[4]. Fatehpur Sikri Fort - Fatehpur Sikri is near Agra and once was the capital of Mughal Emperor Akbar. The architecture of the city was designed by Tahir Das and Dhruv Chawla. Akbar founded the city in 1569 after winning Chittor and Ranthambore.The correct chronological order in which they were built is[1] Tughluqabad Fort, [3] Qutub Minar, [2] Lodi Garden, [4] Fatehpur Sikri. Source : For Tughluqabad Fort -wikipedia.orgFor Qutab Minar - delhitourism.gov.in For Lodi Garden - wikipedia.org For Fatehpur Sikri - tutorialspoint.com ",
            "keyString": "567461s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Name the river on the banks of which the city of Vijayanagar is located?",
            "optionA": "  Kaveri ",
            "optionB": "  Krishna ",
            "optionC": "  Wainganga ",
            "optionD": "  Tungabhadra ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVijayanagara (Sanskrit: \"City of Victory\") was the capital city of the historic Vijayanagara Empire. Located on the banks of the Tungabhadra River, it spread over a large area and included the modern era Group of Monuments at Hampi site in Ballari district and others in and around that district in Karnataka, India. ",
            "keyString": "567520s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The rulers of the Lodi dynasty were",
            "optionA": "  Turks settled in Afghanistan ",
            "optionB": "  Pure Turks ",
            "optionC": "  Pure Afghan ",
            "optionD": "  Timurid Turks ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Lodi dynasty in India arose around 1451 after the Sayyid dynasty. The Lodhi Empire was established by the Ghizlai tribe of the Afghans. ",
            "keyString": "567556s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which century, Qutub Minar of Delhi was built?",
            "optionA": "  12th Century ",
            "optionB": "  13th Century ",
            "optionC": "  14th Century ",
            "optionD": "  11th Century ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tQutub Minar is a tapering tower, which was designed similar to the Minaret of Jam located in Western Afghanistan. The first floor of the tower was built in 12th century. The second, third and fourth floors were built in 13th century and the last floor was completed in 14th century. ",
            "keyString": "567590s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The city of Vijayanagara is also known as",
            "optionA": "  Aravidu ",
            "optionB": "  Chandragiri ",
            "optionC": "  Hampi ",
            "optionD": "  Kondavidu ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHampi a village located on the banks of the Tungabhadra River is regarded as one of the most important world heritage sites in India. It was counted amongst the largest and most prosperous cities of the world during its period of power and vigour. This site that holds significance both historically and architecturally has several monuments, particularly the Virupaksha Temple that is dedicated to the patron deity of the Vijayanagara rulers, Lord Virupaksha, which is why it is often referred as Virupakshapura and Vijayanagara.",
            "keyString": "619685s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Marco-polo, a famous traveller, was native of which country?",
            "optionA": "  Uzbekistan ",
            "optionB": "  Italy ",
            "optionC": "  Morocco ",
            "optionD": "  Russia ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMarco Polo was an Italian merchant, explorer, and writer, born in the Republic of Venice. ",
            "keyString": "619720s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Noor Jahan was the wife of which Mughal emperor?",
            "optionA": "  Babur ",
            "optionB": "  Akbar ",
            "optionC": "  Shahjahan ",
            "optionD": "  Jahangir ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNur Jahan (born Mehr-un-Nissa) (31 May 1577 \u2013 17 December 1645) was the twentieth (and last) wife of the Mughal emperor Jahangir. ",
            "keyString": "619738s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "__________, succeeded to the throne of Ferghana in 1494 when he was only 12 years old",
            "optionA": "  Humayun ",
            "optionB": "  Akbar ",
            "optionC": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionD": "  Babur ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBabur was the son of Umar Sheikh Mirza (Ruler of Ferghana). He succeeded to the throne in 1494 in age of 12 years. ",
            "keyString": "619751s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The remains of the Great Vijayanagar Empire can be found in",
            "optionA": "  Bijapur ",
            "optionB": "  Golconda ",
            "optionC": "  Hampi ",
            "optionD": "  Baroda ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe ruins of Vijaynagar Empire was found at Hampi (Karnataka). The temple town of Hampi was declared the UNESCO world Heritage site in 1986. ",
            "keyString": "619765s18m38h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}